Jeremiah Wadsworth papers
Connecticut Historical Society
Jeremiah Wadsworth Papers
1759-1890s
Connecticut Historical Society, Hartford, Connecticut
Wadworth, Jeremiah, 1743 - 1804.
25 linear feet (50 boxes)
Revolutionary War era business and commisary records.
Biographical Sketch
Jeremiah Wadsworth (1743-1804) was born on July 12, 1743 in Hartford, Connecticut. His father was the Reverend Daniel Wadsworth, a pastor with the First Church of Christ, and his mother was Abigail Talcott, daughter of Connecticut governor Joseph Talcott. As a young man, he worked for ten years on the ships of his uncle Matthew Talcott, beginning at the age of eighteen as a common sailor and eventually becoming a captain. He married Mehitable Russell in 1767 and had three children, Daniel, Harriet, and Catherine.
In April of 1775, Wadsworth was appointed commissary to the revolutionary forces in Connecticut and remained heavily involved with the American struggle for independence for the duration of the war. He became Deputy Commissary General of Purchases to the Continental Army in June of 1777 and rose to the rank of Commissary General in April of 1778. He served in this role until December of 1779, working to acquire all types of provisions for the Continental Army. After resigning from the role of Commissary General, he became commissary to the French Army and Navy in America. He spent the remaining years of the war working to acquire supplies for the French forces and traveled to France at the conclusion of the war.
After the war, Wadsworth continued to be very involved in the politics of his young nation. He attended Connecticut’s state convention for the ratification of the United States constitution in 1788 and voted in favor of ratifying it. He was elected to Congress as a Federalist in 1787 and 1788, serving in 1788. In 1795 Wadsworth was elected to the Connecticut State Legislature and the Executive Council, and he continued to serve on the Executive Council until 1801.
After the war, Wadsworth was involved in a wide variety of business interests, many of which were based in Hartford. He was one of the founders of the Bank of North America and the Hartford Bank, and was an executive with the Bank of New York and United States Bank. He was involved with some of the earliest manufacturing and insurance partnerships in Hartford. Wadsworth also did business as a merchant, was active in the shipping industry, and acquired a great deal of land in the eastern part of the United States. He died in Hartford on April 30, 18041.
1Edward E. Curtis, “Wadsworth, Jeremiah,” in Dictionary of American Biography, ed. Dumas Malone (New York: Charles Scribner’s Sons, 1936), 309-310.
Scope and Content
The Jeremiah Wadsworth Papers are arranged in five series: Correspondence, Financial Documents, Legal Documents, Wadsworth and Carter Papers, and Historical and Genealogical.
Series I: Correspondence contains three subseries: Jeremiah Wadsworth correspondence; Royal Flint, Peter Colt, John Jeffrey, and Barnabas Deane correspondence; and Letter Books. The first subseries contains general and family correspondence written by and addressed to Jeremiah Wadsworth. The letters range in date from 1768 to 1804 and mostly address business, political, and financial matters. It is often difficult to differentiate Jeremiah’s private business interests as a merchant and his work for the revolutionary army, so the general correspondence has been arranged chronologically rather than separated by subject. The exceptions are letters addressed to the company Wadsworth and Carter, which have been placed in Series IV. Much of the correspondence relates to Jeremiah’s work for the revolutionary forces, including his role as commissary to the forces in Connecticut, his later position as Commissary General of the Continental Army, and his subsequent role as commissary to the French Army. These letters address his efforts to acquire, deliver, and pay for supplies for the armies and often express an especially urgent need to acquire grain.
Later correspondence covers Jeremiah Wadsworth’s resignation from the revolutionary forces and the controversy that followed as well as his role in Connecticut’s Constitutional Convention and other political issues. Also addressed in the correspondence are financial matters and Wadsworth’s business interests in property, manufacturing, shipping, insurance, and banking. A few undated miscellaneous documents are also included. Following the general correspondence is correspondence of a personal nature between Jeremiah and various family members. It is arranged chronologically. Most of the letters are communication between Jeremiah, his wife Mehitable, and their children Daniel, Harriet, and Catherine.
The second subseries ranges in date from 1778 to 1801 and contains letters written by and addressed to Royal Flint, Peter Colt, John Jeffrey, and Barnabas Deane. Each of the four men worked closely for or with Jeremiah Wadsworth on various business matters at different times in their careers, and all seem to have been active as merchants during the Revolutionary period. The majority of the letters in this subseries were neither written by nor addressed to Jeremiah Wadsworth, which is why they have been arranged separately. Flint, Colt, Jeffrey, and Deane’s correspondence have each been arranged chronologically. In the cases of correspondence between Wadsworth and these men, the person the letter is addressed to most often determines the subseries it was placed in.
The third and final subseries of Correspondence is made up of letter books containing handwritten copies of Jeremiah Wadsworth’s correspondence from 1778 to 1804. They are arranged chronologically.
Series II: Financial is made up of three subseries. The first subseries contains receipts, invoices, and accounts relating to Jeremiah Wadsworth’s work for the French Army from 1778 to 1797. It is arranged chronologically, with undated material at the end. Researchers interested in this topic should also consult Series IV, which contains financial documents from Wadsworth and Carter’s work for the French Army.
The second subseries contains Jeremiah Wadsworth’s receipts, invoices, accounts, and account books. The material ranges in date from 1767 to 1815. A large portion of the documents relate to his work acquiring supplies for the Continental Army, but his private business interests and personal financial papers are also included. Again, it is often difficult to separate Jeremiah’s work for the Continental Army from his other business as a merchant. The receipts, invoices and accounts have been arranged chronologically. Account books follow these documents and have also been arranged chronologically rather than by subject. Miscellaneous receipts for a man named Joseph Ketchum complete the subseries.
The third subseries contains account books, correspondence regarding financial matters, contracts, notes, account information, and other financial documents belonging to Jeremiah’s son Daniel Wadsworth. The material ranges in date from 1804 to 1848 and has been placed in rough chronological order. A large portion of the material covers Daniel Wadsworth’s financial relationship with the Terry family, who were related to the Wadsworth family by marriage. Much of correspondence and financial information is from Nathaniel Terry, the husband of Jeremiah Wadsworth's daughter Catherine. There are also several documents that relate to the estates of Jeremiah and Mehitable Wadsworth.
Series III: Legal Documents covers the years 1759-1848. The first documents in the series are Hartford deeds issued to Jeremiah Wadsworth, arranged alphabetically according to the last name of the person granting the deed. Following these are a variety of miscellaneous legal documents that are arranged chronologically. They include a certificate of indenture for Jeremiah, government decrees, certificates, a slave bill of sale and emancipation document, private business contracts, and insurance records. Of special interest is the first folder in Box 36, which contains records of treaties Jeremiah Wadsworth made with Native Americans to acquire land on behalf of the United States government.
Finally, this series contains a large amount of land records for both Jeremiah and Daniel Wadsworth. They have been arranged in rough chronological order. A large portion of these documents relate to land the Wadsworth family acquired in Vermont and Genesee County, New York. The land records include several maps as well as contracts, deeds, correspondence, and mortgage certificates.
Series IV: Wadsworth and Carter Papers contains correspondence, receipts, and account books from the company Wadsworth and Carter. Beginning near the end of 1783, the company was briefly known as Wadsworth and Church. The materials in this series range in date from 1780 to 1787. A portion of the correspondence is communication between Jeremiah Wadsworth and his business partner John Carter. Many of these letters discuss their efforts to acquire supplies for the French Army, and a common topic is the often urgent need to acquire grain. Correspondence between the two men also addresses the payment for and delivery of merchandise and purchases of stock and insurance. Additionally, the correspondence includes communication with area merchants who had pledged to deliver supplies to Wadsworth and Carter or their clients. The letters also cover Jeremiah Wadsworth’s trip to France and address political topics such as efforts to establish a national bank of the United States. A few of the letters are in French.
Wadsworth and Carter’s account books covering their work for the French Army have been arranged separately from their other account books and follow the correspondence. Following the French Army accounts are receipts, which also include a few invoices and notes. Receipts from Wadsworth and Carter’s work for the French Army have not been separated from receipts acquired from other business. All are arranged chronologically. Following the receipts are Wadsworth and Carter’s general account books, which complete the series.
Series V: Historical and Genealogical Information contains a variety of materials created after Jeremiah Wadsworth’s death in 1804. It appears to range in date from 1804 to the 1890s, although many of the documents are undated. Much of the correspondence is letters written by and addressed to John F. Morris, who was involved in managing the estates of both Jeremiah and Daniel Wadsworth. Morris was very interested in the genealogy and history of the Wadsworth family. His correspondence includes letters from descendents of Jeremiah Wadsworth such as Rose Terry Cooke, Kate N. Terry, and Katharine Bacon Smith, all of whom discuss the history of the Wadsworth family. Also included are several letters regarding the efforts of Morris and others to locate original portraits of Daniel and Jeremiah Wadsworth. Additionally, the correspondence covers some of Morris’s work to locate and bring together Jeremiah Wadsworth’s papers.
The fourth folder in this series includes a handwritten history of the Wadsworth family and genealogical information. Also of interest is an undated, typewritten 336 page abstract of Jeremiah Wadsworth’s correspondence by George Clinton Fairchild Williams, president of the Connecticut Historical Society from 1919-1922. The abstract provides chronologically arranged descriptions of Wadsworth’s correspondence, with most letters summarized in a short sentence but others described in much more detail. The final folders in the series contain handwritten copies of some of Wadsworth’s correspondence. Most of the copies are undated but appear to be from the 1880s.
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions on access to the collection.
Accruals
The collection is closed.
Download PDF
Subject Headings
Personal Names
Greene, Nathanael, 1742-1786.; Rondineau, Maurice.; Barlow, Joel, 1754-1812.; Champion, Henry, 1723-1797.; Champion, Henry, 1751-1836.; Colt, Peter, 1736-1824.; Deane, Barnabas, b. 1743.; Greene, Catharine.; Hamilton, Alexander 1757-1804.; Hopkins, Theodore.; King, Rufus, 1755-1827.; Knox, Henry, 1750-1806.; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1757-1834.; Mifflin, Thomas, 1744-1800.; Tallmadge, Benjamin, 1754-1835.; Trumbull, David, 1751-1822.; Trumbull, Joseph, 1737-1778.; Wadsworth, Daniel.; Wadsworth, Harriet.; Wadsworth, Mehitable.
Family Names
Terry family.
Corporate Names
United States -- Army -- Supplies and stores.; United States -- Continental Army -- History.
Subjects
Shays’ Rebellion, 1786-1787.
Geographic Names
France -- Commerce -- United States; United States -- Commerce -- France.; Connecticut -- Politics and government.; United States -- History -- Confederation, 1783-1789.; United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783.; United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783 -- Participation, French.; United States -- Politics and government.; West Indies -- Commerce -- United States.; Western Reserve (Ohio).
Contents:
- I. Correspondence, 1768-1804
  - 1. Jeremiah Wadsworth Correspondence, February 1768-June 1774
    - General Correspondence, February 1768-June 1774 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - General Correspondence, November 1774-April 1775 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - General Correspondence, May 1775 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - General Correspondence, June 1775 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - General Correspondence, July 1775 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - General Correspondence, August 1775 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - General Correspondence, September-October 1775 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - General Correspondence, November-December 1775 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - General Correspondence, January-March 1776 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - General Correspondence, April-May 1776 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - General Correspondence, June-July 1776 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - General Correspondence, August 1776 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - General Correspondence, September 1-16, 1776 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - General Correspondence, September 17-30, 1776 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - General Correspondence, October 1-14, 1776 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - General Correspondence, October 15-31, 1776 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - General Correspondence, November-December 1, 1776 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - General Correspondence, December 1776 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - General Correspondence, January-February 13, 1777 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - General Correspondence, February 14-March 1777 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - General Correspondence, April 1777 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - General Correspondence, May 1-15, 1777 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - General Correspondence, May 16-31, 1777 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - General Correspondence, June 1777 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - General Correspondence, July 1-10, 1777 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - General Correspondence, July 11-31 1777 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - General Correspondence, August 1777 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - General Correspondence, September 1777 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - General Correspondence, October 1777 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - General Correspondence, November 1777 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - General Correspondence, December 1777 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - General Correspondence, January 1778 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - General Correspondence, February 1778 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - General Correspondence, March 1778 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - General Correspondence, April-May 12, 1778 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - General Correspondence, May 13-30, 1778 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - General Correspondence, June 1-9, 1778 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - General Correspondence, June 10-30, 1778 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - General Correspondence, July 1-16, 1778 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - General Correspondence, July 16-31, 1778 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - General Correspondence, August 1-15, 1778 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - General Correspondence, August 16-31, 1778 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - General Correspondence, September 1778 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - General Correspondence, October 1-15, 1778 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - General Correspondence, October 16-31, 1778 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - General Correspondence, November 1778 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - General Correspondence, December 1778 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - General Correspondence, January 1779 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - General Correspondence, February 1779 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - General Correspondence, March 1-10, 1779 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - General Correspondence, March 10-31, 1779 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - General Correspondence, April 1-15, 1779 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - General Correspondence, April 16-23, 1779 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - General Correspondence, April 24-30, 1779 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - General Correspondence, May 1-19, 1779 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - General Correspondence, May 20-June 16, 1779 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - General Correspondence, June 17-30, 1779 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - General Correspondence, July 1-9, 1779 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - General Correspondence, July 10-20, 1779 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - General Correspondence, July 21-31, 1779 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - General Correspondence, August 1-10, 1779 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - General Correspondence, August 11-21, 1779 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - General Correspondence, August 22-31, 1779 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - General Correspondence, September 1-10, 1779 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - General Correspondence, September 11-30 1779 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - General Correspondence, October 1-20, 1779 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - General Correspondence, October 21-31, 1779 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - General Correspondence, November 1-14, 1779 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - General Correspondence, November 15-30, 1779 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - General Correspondence, December 1779 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - General Correspondence, January 1780 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - General Correspondence, February 1780 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - General Correspondence, March 1780 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - General Correspondence, April 1780 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - General Correspondence, May 1-15, 1780 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - General Correspondence, May 16-30, 1780 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - General Correspondence, June 1780 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - General Correspondence, July 1780 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - General Correspondence, August 1780 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - General Correspondence, September 1780 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - General Correspondence, October 1780 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - General Correspondence, November 1780 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - General Correspondence, December 1780 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - General Correspondence, January-February 10, 1781 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - General Correspondence, February 11-28, 1781 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - General Correspondence, March 1781 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - General Correspondence, April 1-17, 1781 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - General Correspondence, April 18-30, 1781 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - General Correspondence, May 1781 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - General Correspondence, June 1-15, 1781 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - General Correspondence, June 16-30, 1781 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - General Correspondence, July 1-15, 1781 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - General Correspondence, July 16-31, 1781 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - General Correspondence, August 1781 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - General Correspondence, September 1781 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - General Correspondence, October-December 1781 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - General Correspondence, January-February 1782 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - General Correspondence, March 1-16, 1782 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - General Correspondence, March 17-31, 1782 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - General Correspondence, April 1782 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - General Correspondence, May 1782 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - General Correspondence, June 1782 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - General Correspondence, July 1782 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - General Correspondence, August 1782 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - General Correspondence, September 1782 (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - General Correspondence, October 1782 (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - General Correspondence, November 1782-January 1783 (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - General Correspondence, February-March 1783 (Box 10, Folder 15)
    - General Correspondence, April-May 1783 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - General Correspondence, June-October 1783 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - General Correspondence, November 1783-January 1784 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - General Correspondence, February-March 1784 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - General Correspondence, April-July 1784 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - General Correspondence, August-October 1784 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - General Correspondence, November-December 1784 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - General Correspondence, January-February 1785 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - General Correspondence, March 1785 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - General Correspondence, April-May 1785 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - General Correspondence, June-July 1785 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - General Correspondence, August-September 1785 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - General Correspondence, October 1785 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - General Correspondence, November 1785 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - General Correspondence, December 1785 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - General Correspondence, January-April 1786 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - General Correspondence, May-June 1786 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - General Correspondence, July-August 1786 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - General Correspondence, September-October 1786 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - General Correspondence, November-December 15, 1786 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - General Correspondence, December 16, 1786 – January 1787 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - General Correspondence, February-March 1787 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - General Correspondence, April 1787 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - General Correspondence, May 1787 (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - General Correspondence, June 1787 (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - General Correspondence, July 1787 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - General Correspondence, August 1787 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - General Correspondence, September-October 1787 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - General Correspondence, November-December 1787 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - General Correspondence, January 1788 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - General Correspondence, February 1788 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - General Correspondence, March 1788 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - General Correspondence, April 1788 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - General Correspondence, May 1788 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - General Correspondence, June-August 1788 (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - General Correspondence, September-October 1788 (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - General Correspondence, November 1788 (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - General Correspondence, December 1788 (Box 13, Folder 13)
    - General Correspondence, January 1789 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - General Correspondence, February 1789 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - General Correspondence, March-April 1789 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - General Correspondence, May-June 1789 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - General Correspondence, July-August 1789 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - General Correspondence, September-November 1789 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - General Correspondence, December 1789 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - General Correspondence, January-March 1790 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - General Correspondence, April-July 1790 (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - General Correspondence, August-September 1790 (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - General Correspondence, October-December 1790 (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - General Correspondence, January-February 1791 (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - General Correspondence, March-April 1791 (Box 14, Folder 13)
    - General Correspondence, May-June 1791 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - General Correspondence, July-September 1791 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - General Correspondence, October-November 1791 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - General Correspondence, December 1791-January 1792 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - General Correspondence, February-March 1792 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - General Correspondence, April-May 1792 (Box 15, Folder 6)